Finding Aid for Claribel Baird Halstead papers, 1920-2000
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Claribel Baird Halstead papers 1920-2000
Halstead, Claribel Baird, 1904-
1 oversize folders
8 linear feet
2008018 Aa 2
Professor of Speech at the University of Michigan and active participant in local, national, and university theater. The collection includes correspondence, press, and programs and photos documenting various theatrical productions.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection was transferred from Special Collections of the Harlan Hatcher library of the University of Michigan (donor no. 1278
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Claribel Buford was born on December 9, 1904 in Van Alstyne, Texas. In 1925, she earned a Bachelor of Arts degree in English from Oklahoma College for Women. She earned a Master of Arts in Speech from the University of Michigan in 1936. For twenty years, 1927-47, Claribel taught speech and theater in Oklahoma.
In 1948 she accepted an associate professorship with the University of Michigan Department of Speech and moved to Ann Arbor. She earned a full professorship in 1963 and continued to teach until her retirement in 1974. She directed over 40 plays and taught several courses, including a course that she created in Greek Theater.
Claribel was also a talented actress and performed in productions both at Michigan and elsewhere. She was active within the profession, serving on various boards including that of the American Educational Theater Association and the College of Fellows of the American Theater Association. She received multiple awards throughout her career, most notably the Michigan Governor's Award for Concerned Citizens of the Arts in Michigan in 1989. Claribel was a strong advocate for theater at Michigan and helped to establish the Association of Producing Artists, the first professional theater company at the University of Michigan.
Claribel was married twice and took the name of her husband each time. In 1929 she married Bernard Baird. They had one son, Jerome, together before Bernard died in 1948. Claribel remarried in 1952 to William Halstead, also a University of Michigan theater professor. William died in 1983. Claribel died of pneumonia at the age of 99 in April 2003.
This collection documents Claribel Baird Halstead’s life as an educator, theatrical director, and actress. It provides insight into the development and history of theater at the University of Michigan and into Claribel’s specific contributions. The collection is divided into five series: Personal Papers, Professional Papers, Audiovisual Materials, Theater Programs, and Published plays.
Subjects:
Actresses--United States.; College theater--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Halstead, Claribel Baird, 1904-; Theater--United States.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Speech.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Women in the theater.
Genre Terms:
Motion pictures.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Theater programs.
- Personal Papers
  The Personal Papers series (2.5 linear feet) includes correspondence, memorabilia, and photographs documenting Claribel's relationships with colleagues, students, and family. Also included are files related to the awards Claribel received throughout her career and files documenting the establishment and administration of the William and Claribel Halstead Scholarship. A set of theater programs documenting productions at the University of Michigan, in Ann Arbor and around Michigan are also included in this series.
  - Alumni
    - 1994 Reunion, Beverly Hills (Box 1)
    - 1995 Reunion, New York City (Box 1)
    - General (Box 1)
    - Jones, James Earl (Box 1)
  - Awards (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Chapel, Robert (Box 1)
    - Death of William Halstead (Box 1)
    - General
      - 1930-1939 (Box 1)
      - 1940-1949 (Box 1)
      - 1950-1959 (Box 1)
      - 1960-1969 (Box 1)
      - 1970-1979 (Box 1)
      - 1980-1989 (Box 1)
      - 1990-2000 (Box 1)
      - Undated (Box 1)
    - Halstead, William (Box 1)
    - Miller Theater (Box 1)
    - Retirement (Box 1)
    - Stage Adaptation of "The Odyssey" (Box 1)
    - Theater Abroad (Box 1)
    - University of Michigan (Box 1)
  - Diaries and Journals (Box 1)
  - Memorabilia
    - Death of Bernard Baird (Box 1)
    - Death of William Halstead (Box 1)
    - General, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Oklahoma, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Wedding (Box 2)
  - Photographs
    - Family, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Portraits of Claribel Baird Halstead (Box 2)
    - Unidentified (Box 2)
  - Posters (Box 2)
  - Programs, 6 folders (Box 3)
  - Scholarship Fund, 2 folders (Box 3)
- Professional Papers
  The Professional Papers series (2.5 linear feet) includes files documenting Claribel's participation in various professional groups. The Production Files within this series contain materials documenting theatrical productions in which Claribel participated, usually as an actor or director. Her teaching materials, documenting a range of courses from Greek theater to Modern Drama to women in theater, are also included in the series. Materials relating to Claribel's original research, publications and presentations constitute a small portion of this series.
  - 1961 Silver Jubilee (Box 3)
  - Association of Producing Artists, Inc. (Box 3)
  - College of Fellows of the American Theater (Box 3)
  - Correspondence
    - General (Box 3)
    - Student (Box 3)
  - Departmental Publications (Box 3)
  - Production Files
    - Antigone (Box 3)
    - The Enchanted (Box 3)
    - Greek Theater (Box 3)
    - Green Growth (Box 3)
    - I Knock at the Door (Box 3)
    - The Importance of Being Earnest (Box 3)
    - The Mad Woman of Chaillot (Box 3)
      (see also oversize folder)
    - Murder in the Cathedral (Box 4)
    - The Odyssey: A Modern Sequel (Box 4)
    - Peer Gynt (Box 4)
    - Prometheus (Box 4)
    - The Rivals (Folder 1)
    - Romeo and Juliet (Box 4)
    - The Royal Family (Box 4)
    - School for Husbands (Box 4)
    - Shaw, George Bernard (Box 4)
    - The Stations of the Cross (Box 4)
    - Thyestes (Box 4)
    - The Trojan Women (Box 4)
    - Under Milkwood (Box 4)
    - Various Productions
      - Contracts, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - General, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - Permissions and Royalties (Box 4)
      - Posters and Schematics (Box 4)
  - Published Works and Presentations
    - General (Box 4)
    - "Master Teachers of Theater" (Box 4)
  - Research
    - Dramatists and Theater Personalities (Box 4)
    - History of Ann Arbor Theater (Box 5)
  - Resumes (Box 5)
  - Teaching Materials
    - 18th Century Theater (Box 5)
    - The Bacchae (Box 5)
    - Comedies (Box 5)
    - Euripedes (Box 5)
    - Greek Chorus (Box 5)
    - Greek Theater (Box 5)
    - Lorca, Federico Garcia (Box 5)
    - Modern Drama (Box 5)
    - Moore, Marianne (Box 5)
    - Poetry, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Scenes (Box 5)
    - Shakespeare (Box 5)
    - Shaw's Women (Box 5)
    - Skits (Box 5)
    - Sophocles (Box 5)
    - Speeches (Box 5)
    - Tragedy (Box 5)
    - Women in Theater (Box 5)
  - Theatrical Publications (Box 5)
- Audiovisual Materials
  The Audiovisual Materials series (1 linear foot) includes audiotape recordings of various theatrical performances including "The Odyssey," "The Stations of the Cross," "Thyestes." Also included is a motion picture film element entitled "Grooves" and dated "Summer 1959."
  - Film: Grooves, 1959 (Box 5)
  - Sound recordings, 7" reel-to-reel; 1/4 in.
    - The Odyssey undated (Box 5)
    - The Odyssey: A Modern Sequel 1971 (Box 5)
    - The Stations of the Cross 1971 (Box 5)
    - Thyestes 1967 (Box 5)
- Theater Programs, in bound volumes
  The Theatre Programs series (3 linear feet) consists of programs of theatrical productions in England and other European countries. The programs have been bound into volumes and date from 1952 to 1968. Interspersed in the volumes are occasional notes, letters, and memorabilia.
  - Europe programs and miscellaneous souvenir materials 1952, 1 volumes (Box 6)
  - Europe programs
    - 1956-1957 Books I-III, 3 volumes (Box 6)
    - 1956-1957 Book IV, 1 volumes (Box 7)
    - 1964, 3 volumes (Box 7)
    - 1964, 1 volumes (Box 8)
    - 1967, 1 volumes (Box 8)
    - 1968, 1 volumes (Box 8)
  - Glyndebourne Festival Opera programs 1959-1965 (Box 8)
- Published plays
  The Published Plays series (5 volumes) are from productions in which Claribel Halstead was in some way connected. The volumes include numerous notations.
  - The Ship; A Play in Three Acts by St. John G. Ervine ( 1927 ) (Box 8)
  - What A Life; Comedy in Three Acts by Clifford Goldsmith ( 1939 ) (Box 8)
  - Journey to Jerusalem; A Play in Three Acts by Maxwell Anderson ( 1940 ) (Box 8)
  - I Remember Mama; A Play in Two Acts by John van Druten ( 1945 ) (Box 8)
  - A Masque of Reason by Robert Frost ( 1945 ) (Box 8)